<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Whereas we have been necessarily occasioned to take especial notice, that His Majesties revenue arising by hearths, firing places and stoves within this kingdom, hath of late become very much impaired, and still continues deeply in arrear ... by the Lord Lieutenant and Council, Ormonde.</title>
            <author>Ireland. Lord Lieutenant (1661-1669 : Ormonde)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46213</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36979</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16170504</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16170504</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104971</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46213)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104971)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1595:76)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Whereas we have been necessarily occasioned to take especial notice, that His Majesties revenue arising by hearths, firing places and stoves within this kingdom, hath of late become very much impaired, and still continues deeply in arrear ... by the Lord Lieutenant and Council, Ormonde.</title>
                  <author>Ireland. Lord Lieutenant (1661-1669 : Ormonde)</author>
                  <author>Ormonde, James Butler, Duke of, 1610-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2] leaves.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Crooke ... and are to besold [sic] by Samuel Dancer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666 [1667]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from first 6 lines of text.</note>
                  <note>Statement of responsibility transposed from head of title.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"Given at the Council chamber in Dublin, the 21 day of March, 1666" [1667]--leaf [2]</note>
                  <note>Broadside in [2] leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Society of Antiquaries Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hearth-money --  Ireland.</term>
               <term>Taxation --  Ireland.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1649-1775.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Politics and government --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:104971:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>BY THE Lord Lieutenant and Council.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>ORMONDE,</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas We have been neceſſarily occaſioned to take eſpecial notice, That His Majeſties Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue ariſing by Hearths, Firing places and Stoves within this Kingdom, hath of late be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come very much impaired, and ſtill continues deeply in arrear, and unſatisfied into His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Exchequer, partly through the great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement and obſtructions given unto His Majeſties Officers, and their Deputies, in the improvement and collection of the ſame, and the miſdemeanors of ſeveral perſons who have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to conceal many Hearthes, Firing places and Stoves, which by the Law are chargeable, and partly by the obſtinacy of ſuch perſons of Quality, and Commanders of His Majeſties Caſtles and Forts, as refuſe to permit His Majeſties Officers, or their Deputies to enter into their houſes to view and number the ſeveral Hearths, Firing places and Stoves therein, or to take Diſtreſſes for the duty ariſing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; as alſo through the Combination of ſeveral Inhabitants, who pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely to defraud His Majeſtie, do take upon them to ſhelter the Diſtreſſes of their neighbours, who by their Delinquency are become liable thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and laſtly through the negligence or counivance of ſeveral Magiſtrates, Miniſters, Conſtables and other Officers, who have given too much countenance to ſuch undue proceedings, and too little aſſiſtance to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties ſaid Officers and their Deputies, in levying and improving the ſaid Revenue, whom they have in ſome places ſuffered to be reproached, and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently abuſed, without puniſhing the Malefactors, although it be the duty of all Conſtables and other inferior Officers, to accompany, aſſiſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend His Majeſties Officers and their Deputies, as well in the viewing and numbering of the ſeveral Hearths, Firing places and Stoves, as in their collecting of the Revenue ariſing thereout, and the duty of all Iuſtices
<pb facs="tcp:104971:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
of Peace and chief Magiſtrates, in their reſpective places and callings, and with the utmoſt of their Authority, to ſupport His Majeſties ſaid Revenue, ſo well eſtabliſhed by Law, and ſo neceſſary to the ſafety and defenſe of His Majeſtie and His good Subjects: We therefore being reſolved to redreſs the aforeſaid abuſes, and for the time to come to remove all impediments to the levying and collecting of the ſaid Revenue, and to take a ſtrict account of all ſuch perſons as ſhall hereafter be found wanting in their duty to His Majeſtie, and to the Laws of this Kingdom, have thought fit to publiſh and declare, That all arrears of the ſaid Revenue, as well thoſe which were incurred from the <hi>24th</hi> day of <hi>June, 1665.</hi> to the <hi>25th</hi> of <hi>March 1666.</hi> as thoſe which have accrued ſince, and all future growing duties ſhall forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and with all poſſible ſpeed, and diligence be collected and levyed by and paid unto His Majeſties reſpective Officers and their Deputies aforeſaid, publiſhed, nominated and appointed for that purpoſe by our Proclamation of the <hi>15th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt, 1666.</hi> and no others; And we do hereby ſtrictly charge and command all Iuſtices of Peace, chief Magiſtrates, Conſtables and all other Officers and Miniſters of Iuſtice, whom it doth or may concern, that upon pain of being proceeded againſt as contemners of His Majeſties au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and as perſons ill affected to the Peace and ſafety of this his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, they be ayding and aſſiſting to His Majeſties ſaid Officers and their Deputies, aſwel in viewing and numbring the ſaid Hearths, Firing places and Stoves, as in collecting and levying all ſuch ſum or ſums of money as is already become due, and in arrear, or which hereafter ſhall become due and payable for or by reaſon of the dutie ariſing out of the ſaid Hearths, Firing places and Stoves, And herein we do expect and require from them, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them ſuch vigorous and effectual aſſiſtance to be given to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſaid Officers and their Deputies, that all concealments of any Hearths, Firing places and Stoves may be ſpeedily detected, all illegal and undue practices for exempting any perſons lyable, or ſheltering of their diſtreſſes prevented, all obſtructions in the collecting of His Majeſties ſaid Revenue removed, and all perſons who ſhall deny admiſſion into their Houſes, or any wayes affront, or abuſe His Majeſties ſaid Officers or their Deputies in word, or deed exemplarily puniſhed; And we do hereby will and require all Sheriffs, Mayors and Bayliffs in the ſeveral and reſpective Counties, Cities and Towns Corporate of this His Majeſties Kingdom to cauſe this our Proclamation to be publiſhed in all and every the Market places within their limits upon ſome Market day within fourteen dayes next after there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt hereof, as they will anſwer the contrary at their perils.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at the Council Chamber in <hi>Dublin,</hi> 
                  <date>the 21 day of <hi>March,</hi> 1666.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Ja. Armachanus.</item>
                     <item>Mich. Dublin. Canc.</item>
                     <item>Oſſory.</item>
                     <item>R. Coote.</item>
                     <item>Hen. Midenſis.</item>
                     <item>Kingſton.</item>
                     <item>Fra. Aungier.</item>
                     <item>Santry.</item>
                     <item>J. Temple.</item>
                     <item>Rob. Byron.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
               <lb/>
GOD Save the KING.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Dublin,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Crooke,</hi> Printer to the Kings Moſt Excellent Majeſtie, and are to be ſold by <hi>Samuel Dancer</hi> in <hi>Caſtleſtreet.</hi> 1666.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
